John Spencer Bassett Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
John Spencer Bassett Papers 1770-1978 1894-1928
MSS81299
Bassett, John Spencer, 1867-1928
25,450 items
63 containers plus 5 oversize
26.8 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Historian, editor, and educator. Correspondence, diaries and journals, lectures, speeches, writings, research material, subject files, family correspondence, and collected historical manuscripts documenting Bassett's career as historian, editor and university professor.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Adams, Herbert B. (Herbert Baxter), 1850-1901--Correspondence.; Andrews, Charles McLean, 1863-1943--Correspondence.; Bassett, Jessie Lewellin--Correspondence.; Bassett, John Spencer, 1867-1928.; Bassett, Margaret Byrd--Correspondence.; Bassett, Richard H. (Richard Horace), 1900-1995--Correspondence.; Battle, Kemp P. (Kemp Plummer), 1831-1919--Correspondence.; Boyd, William K. (William Kenneth), 1879-1938--Correspondence.; Cable, George Washington, 1844-1925--Correspondence.; Claiborne, William C. C. (William Charles Cole), 1775-1817--Correspondence.; Crowell, J. Franklin (John Franklin), 1857-1931--Correspondence.; Daniels, Josephus, 1862-1948--Correspondence.; Dodd, William E. (William Edward), 1869-1940--Correspondence.; Donelson, Stockley, -approximately 1804.; Earl, Ralph, 1751-1801.; Hart, Albert Bushnell, 1854-1943--Correspondence.; Jackson, Andrew, 1767-1845.; Jameson, J. Franklin (John Franklin), 1859-1937--Correspondence.; Page, Walter Hines, 1855-1918--Correspondence.; Phillips, Ulrich Bonnell, 1877-1934--Correspondence.; Roane, Archibald, 1759-1819--Correspondence.; Trent, William P. (William Peterfield), 1862-1939--Correspondence.; Tyrrell, William.; Watson, Henry, 1810-; Williams, Benjamin, 1751-1814--Correspondence.; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924--Correspondence.
Organizations
American Historical Association.; League of Nations.; Smith College--Faculty.; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.)--Faculty.
Subjects
Editors.; Educational change--Southern states.; Slavery--North Carolina.; Yazoo Fraud, 1795.
Places
North Carolina--History--Regulator Insurrection, 1766-1771.; North Carolina--History.; Southern States--Politics and government--1865-1950.; Southern States--Race relations.; United States--Politics and government--1865-1933.
Titles
South Atlantic quarterly.
Occupations
Editors.; Educators.; Historians.
Acquisition Information
The papers of John Spencer Bassett, historian, editor, and educator, were given to the Library of Congress by his son, Richard H. Bassett, in 1991. An addition was given by James Lutzweiler in 1993.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of John Spencer Bassett are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1867, Sept. 10 Born, Tarboro, N.C.
1888 B.A., Trinity College, Randolph County, N.C. (later Duke University, Durham, N.C.)
1890 Instructor in English, Trinity College, Randolph County, N.C. Founded "9019," student scholarship group, Trinity College, Randolph County, N.C.
1892 Married Jessie Lewellin
1894 Ph.D., Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, Md. Published The Constitutional Beginnings of North Carolina, 1663-1729 (Baltimore: The Johns Hopkins Press. 73 pp.) Published The Regulators of North Carolina, 1765-1771 (Washington: United States Government Printing Office. 72 pp.)
1894 1906 Professor of history, Trinity College, Randolph County, N.C.
1895 Published Suffrage in the State of North Carolina, 1776-1861 (Washington: American Historical Association. 17 pp.)
1896 Published Slavery and Servitude in the Colony of North Carolina (Baltimore: The Johns Hopkins Press. 86 pp.)
1898 Published Anti-Slavery Leaders of North Carolina (Baltimore: The Johns Hopkins Press. 74 pp.)
1899 Published Slavery in the State of North Carolina (Baltimore: The Johns Hopkins Press. 111 pp.)
1901 Founder and editor, South Atlantic Quarterly (resigned as editor, 1905) Published The Writings of "Colonel William Byrd, of Westover, in Virginia, Esqr." (Garden City, N.Y.: Doubleday, Page, & Co.)
1903 Published "Stirring Up the Fires of Race Antipathy." South Atlantic Quarterly 2 (Oct. 1903): 107-113
1906 1928 Professor of history, Smith College, Northampton, Mass.
1906 Published The Federalist System, 1789-1801 (New York: Harper and Brothers. 327 pp.)
1911 Published Life of Andrew Jackson (Garden City, N.Y.: Doubleday, Page, & Co. 2 vols.)
1913 Published A Short History of the United States (New York: Macmillan Co. 885 pp.)
1916 Published The Plain Story of American History (New York: Macmillan Co. 545 pp.)
1917 Published The Middle Group of American Historians (New York: Macmillan Co. 324 pp.) Published Correspondence of George Bancroft and Jared Sparks, 1823-1832 (Northampton, Mass.: Department of History, Smith College. 77 pp.)
1918 Published The Lost Fruits of Waterloo (New York: Macmillan Co. 289 pp.)
1919 Published Our War With Germany: A History (New York: Alfred A. Knopf, Inc. 386 pp.)
1919 1928 Secretary, American Historical Association
1920 Chairman, advisory group, Democratic National Committee
1922 Published Letters of Francis Parkman to Pierre Margry (Northampton, Mass: Department of History, Smith College. 86 pp.)
1925 Published The Southern Plantation Overseer as Revealed in His Letters (Northampton, Mass.: Department of History of Smith College. 280 pp.)
1926 Published Expansion and Reform, 1889-1926 (New York: Longmans, Green, and Co. 355 pp.)
1926 1935 Published Correspondence of Andrew Jackson (Washington, D.C.: Carnegie Institution of Washington. 7 vols.)
1928 Published Makers of A New Nation (New Haven: Yale University Press. 344 pp.) Published The League of Nations: A Chapter in World Politics (New York: Longmans, Green, and Co. 415 pp.)
1928, Jan. 27 Died, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of John Spencer Bassett (1867-1928) span the years 1770-1978, with the bulk of the material dating from 1894 to 1928. The collection documents Bassett's teaching careers at Trinity College (later Duke University) in North Carolina and at Smith College in Massachusetts; his research and writings, including his seminal biography of Andrew Jackson and sometimes controversial writings on race relations; and his secretaryship of the American Historical Association. The papers are arranged in eight series: Diaries and Journals, Family Correspondence, General Correspondence, Collected Historical Manuscripts, Subject File, Lectures and Speeches, Research and Writings, and Oversize.
Diaries and journals kept by Bassett date between 1905 and 1927. Bassett was an inconsistent diarist who frequently picked up and dropped the practice of recording his daily activities. For many years, he maintained what he called a "literary record" in which he charted the daily progress of his research and writing. During other periods, he kept a more traditional diary in which he described conversations, interviews, meetings, colleagues, and national events, often at great length. He began the diary in the wake of what became known as the "Bassett Affair." In 1903, Bassett published "Stirring Up the Fires of Race Antipathy" in the South Atlantic Quarterly, a journal he founded while teaching at Trinity College. The article and its contention that Booker T. Washington was the greatest southerner apart from Robert E. Lee born in the past hundred years touched off a storm of controversy led chiefly by Josephus Daniels, editor of the Raleigh News and Observer. One of the first entries in Bassett's 1905 diary records his decision to resign as editor of the South Atlantic Quarterly. A later entry provides a detailed account of his meeting with Theodore Roosevelt, who agreed to speak on behalf of academic freedom at a stop in Durham, North Carolina, during his southern tour in 1905.
The Family Correspondence series contains lengthy correspondence between Bassett and his wife, Jessie Lewellin Bassett, written on an almost daily basis during academic breaks when Bassett taught summer school, researched, and attended American Historical Association meetings, and during Jessie Bassett's European travels. Apart from discussing family matters, Bassett's letters relate events and developments connected with his research, writing, and teaching. The series also includes correspondence between the Bassetts and their children, Richard H. Bassett and Margaret Byrd Bassett. Much of the correspondence between Richard Bassett and his parents occurred while he was a student at Phillips Academy, Andover, Massachusetts, 1914-1915, and while he studied art in Europe.
The General Correspondence spans the length of Bassett's professional career. His early correspondence, dating from 1894 to 1906, consists largely of incoming correspondence. Much of it concerns Bassett's early research on North Carolina topics, such as the Regulator movement, slavery, and the antislavery movement, and includes letters from Hinton Rowan Helper and Daniel R. Goodloe. Letters from historian Herbert Baxter Adams reveal his ongoing mentorship after Bassett completed his doctoral work at Johns Hopkins University. A significant portion of Bassett's early correspondence concerns Trinity College. Bassett, who had been considered for Trinity's presidency in 1894, promoted scholarship at Trinity through his founding of the South Atlantic Quarterly in 1901 and his efforts to develop the library's book and manuscript holdings. The "Bassett Affair" is discussed in some of these letters.
Bassett's correspondence reveals his interest in southern race relations, politics, and educational reform. Correspondence with southern colleagues continued following Bassett's departure from the South in 1906. Over time, however, Bassett's focus on southern issues lessened and a greater percentage of his later correspondence concerns his subsequent research and writing, in particular his work on Andrew Jackson, and his administrative responsibilities with the American Historical Association and Smith College, his interest and involvement in national politics, and his support of the League of Nations. Prominent correspondents in the General Correspondence series include Charles McLean Andrews, Kemp P. Battle, William Kenneth Boyd, George Washington Cable, John Franklin Crowell, Josephus Daniels, William Edward Dodd, Robert L. Flowers, Albert Bushnell Hart, J. Franklin Jameson, John C. Kilgo, Edwin Mims, Walter Hines Page, Ulrich Bonnell Phillips, William Peterfield Trent, and Woodrow Wilson.
The papers also include a collection of historical manuscripts either purchased by Bassett or given to him by students and friends. While some of these were collected largely for their autographs, many have greater informational value. Among the more significant collections of papers is an exchange of letters between governors Benjamin Williams of North Carolina, Archibald Roane of Tennessee, and William Charles Coles Claiborne of the Mississippi Territory in 1802. These concern the extradition of Stockley Donelson and William Tyrrell, both implicated in western land frauds. The series also contains papers of artist Ralph E. W. Earl, who married Jane Caffery, a niece of Andrew Jackson, in 1818. Earl, who became known as "portrait painter to the king," enjoyed a close relationship with Jackson. He resided at the White House during Jackson's presidency and died at the Hermitage in Tennessee in 1837. Bassett also acquired papers of Henry Watson, a lawyer, banker, and planter who left his native Connecticut in the 1830s and settled in Alabama. Watson's diary, written between 1830 and 1831, and his correspondence, spanning the years 1830-1871, contain numerous references to southern life, economic conditions, politics, and sectionalism. The Watson family papers also include correspondence from Watson's grandfather to his father while the latter was trying to establish himself as a merchant in New York City between 1817 and 1820. Bassett collected various literary collections such as the papers of Sidney Woollett, Layton W. Crippen, and the publishing firm of Stone and Kimball. An alphabetical list of prominent correspondents in this portion of the papers is appended to the register.
The Subject File documents Bassett's professional associations, political activities, and, to a lesser extent, his teaching career. The major portion of the series pertains to Bassett's duties as secretary of the American Historical Association from 1919 to 1928. Files relating to the organization include correspondence, committee and executive council minutes and reports, and financial statements. Another sizeable group of material concerns Bassett's chairmanship of a Democratic National Committee advisory group during the 1920 presidential campaign. The group, charged with devising general strategy for the James M. Cox-Franklin D. Roosevelt campaign, focused most of its efforts on increasing public support for the League of Nations. Bassett sought to influence public opinion by soliciting and publishing articles written by prominent individuals in support of the League. The Subject File also includes newspaper clippings pertaining to Bassett's activities at Trinity College and correspondence, minutes, and reports relating to his teaching and administrative duties at Smith College. Miscellaneous material includes condolence letters on Bassett's death, notebooks, and publishing contracts.
Bassett's lecture files include complete drafts of lectures, outlines, and notes. More than half of these are identified as having been delivered at Smith College. Unidentified lectures include what appear to be Bassett's earliest lectures, some of which are written on Trinity College stationery. Bassett's speeches are grouped by topic since few are dated or have formal titles. Both his speeches and his lectures are useful in tracing Bassett's views on race relations, southern history and culture, and developments in the historical profession.
The Research and Writings series reflects Bassett's contributions to historical research through his exploration of slavery and the antislavery movement, plantation management, and nineteenth-century American historiography, as well as through his biography of Andrew Jackson and editorship of Jackson's letters. Bassett's research files include notes from his research in manuscript repositories, conversations and interviews, and access to privately held manuscripts. Correspondence in the research files pertains to his research on slavery in North Carolina and the search for letters of Andrew Jackson. The writings file contains drafts of many of Bassett's books as well as a large group of unidentified and miscellaneous writings and a collection of literary and poetical manuscripts, many of which pertain to southern themes.
Organization of the Papers
The collection is arranged in eight series:
Diaries and Journals, 1905-1927
Family Correspondence, 1889-1932
General Correspondence, 1891-1930
Collected Historical Manuscripts, 1770-1927
Subject File, 1895-1978
Lectures and Speeches, 1902-1926
Research and Writings, 1884-1928
Oversize, 1856-1920
Container List
- Diaries and Journals, 1905-1927 (Box 1-2)
  Diaries and journals kept by Bassett.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1905-1924, (7 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1925-1927 (Box 2)
- Family Correspondence, 1889-1932 (Box 2-15)
  Correspondence between Bassett and his wife, Jessie Lewellin Bassett, and from each of them to their children, Richard H. Bassett and Margaret Byrd Bassett.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of family member and therein chronologically.
  - Bassett, Jessie Lewellin (wife) (Box 2)
    - June 1889-Dec. 1902, (11 folders)
    - Mar. 1903-Aug. 1911, (8 folders) (Box 3)
    - Sept. 1911-Feb. 1912, (8 folders) (Box 4)
    - Mar.-Sept. 1912, (6 folders) (Box 5)
    - Feb. 1913-Apr. 1921, (10 folders) (Box 6)
    - May 1921-Jan. 1925, (10 folders) (Box 7)
    - Feb. 1925-Mar. 1927, undated, (4 folders) (Box 8)
  - Bassett, Margaret Byrd (daughter)
    - May 1911-Apr. 1924, (6 folders)
    - May 1924-Dec. 1927, undated, (7 folders) (Box 9)
  - Bassett, Richard H. (son)
    - circa 1903-1914, (2 folders)
    - 1915-1916, (8 folders) (Box 10)
    - 1917-1919, (8 folders) (Box 11)
    - 1920-1922, (8 folders) (Box 12)
    - 1923-1925, (8 folders) (Box 13)
    - 1926-1927, undated, (6 folders) (Box 14)
  - Other family members
    - 1892-1902, (2 folders)
    - 1903-1932, undated, (6 folders) (Box 15)
- General Correspondence, 1891-1930 (Box 15-29)
  Correspondence with related attachments.
  - Feb. 1891-June 1896, (3 folders) (Box 15)
  - July 1896-Dec. 1901, (9 folders) (Box 16)
  - Jan. 1902-Dec. 1905, (8 folders) (Box 17)
  - Jan. 1906-Dec. 1908, (9 folders) (Box 18)
  - Jan. 1909-Oct. 1911, (8 folders) (Box 19)
  - Nov. 1911-Apr. 1914, (8 folders) (Box 20)
  - May 1914-June 1916, (7 folders) (Box 21)
  - July 1916-Dec. 1917, (8 folders) (Box 22)
  - Jan. 1918-Aug. 1919, (7 folders) (Box 23)
  - Sept. 1919-Feb. 1921, (8 folders) (Box 24)
  - Mar. 1921-July 1922, (9 folders) (Box 25)
  - Aug. 1922-Apr. 1924, (9 folders) (Box 26)
  - May 1924-June 1925, (7 folders) (Box 27)
  - July 1925-Aug. 1926, (8 folders) (Box 28)
  - Sept. 1926-Jan. 1930, undated, (9 folders) (Box 29)
- Collected Historical Manuscripts, 1770-1927 (Box 30-33)
  Correspondence, diaries, receipts, legal documents, writings, photographs, and printed matter collected by Bassett.
  Arranged alphabetically by name, topic, or type of material. A list of prominent correspondents is contained in an appendix.
  - Alger, Abby L., 1881-1885, undated (Box 30)
  - Alger, William Rounseville, 1856-1869
  - Ashmead, H. G., 1854-1897
  - "A" miscellaneous, 1781-1897, undated
  - Belden, William, 1864-1884, undated
  - "B" miscellaneous, 1772-1883, undated
  - Chard, Louise Cable, 1913-1918, undated
  - Clark, Cynthia Williams, 1869-1878, undated, (4 folders)
  - Clarke, Chauncey, 1838-1852
  - Crippen, Layton W.
    - Correspondence, 1908-1915, undated, (3 folders)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1913-1914
  - "C-D" miscellaneous, 1786-1913, undated, (2 folders)
  - Earl, Ralph E. W., family (Box 31)
    - Earl, Jane Caffery, 1815-1818, undated, (2 folders)
    - Earl, Ralph E. W.
      - Correspondence
        - From, 1818-1829
        - To, 1816-1837, undated, (9 folders)
      - Inventory of possessions at the Hermitage, Nashville, Tenn., at time of death, 1838-1839
      - Passport, 1815
      - Writings, 1813-1825, undated
  - Jackson, Andrew, correspondence to, 1828-1840, undated
    - Miscellany, undated
  - Everett, Edward, 1839, 1854 (Box 32)
  - Fitch, John, 1878-1883, undated
  - "F-G" miscellaneous, 1770-1886, undated
  - Hamlin, Lizzie Lord, 1863-1894
  - "H-L" miscellaneous, 1792-1912, undated, (2 folders)
  - Marsh, Luther R., 1882-1886, undated
  - Marvin, Samuel W., 1890-1913, undated
  - Massachusetts, Northampton, 1869-1870, undated
  - "M-O" miscellaneous, 1791-1909, undated
  - Pennsylvania, 1788-1856, undated
  - Preble, Edward E., 1861-1867, undated
  - Printed ephemera, 1776-1889
  - Pyle, Walter L., 1896-1918, undated
  - "P" miscellaneous, 1810-1877
  - Roosevelt, Theodore, autograph manuscript pages from The Winning of the West, undated
  - "R" miscellaneous, 1803-1839
  - Stanwood, Joann, 1837-1840
  - Stone and Kimball, 1894-1897, undated
  - "S-V" miscellaneous, 1775-1865, undated, (2 folders)
  - Watson, Henry, family
    - Correspondence
      - circa 1803-1830, (2 folders)
      - 1831-1871, undated, (4 folders) (Box 33)
    - Diaries and reminiscences, 1830-1831, 1927
    - Miscellany, 1802-1869, undated
    - Printed matter, 1843-1884, undated See also Oversize
  - Western land fraud, 1798-1802
  - Woollett, Sidney, 1875-1902, undated
  - "W-Y" miscellaneous, 1811-1904, undated
  - Unidentified, 1816-1883, undated
- Subject File, 1895-1978 (Box 33-43)
  Correspondence, minutes, reports, financial records, academic files, address book, notebook, and printed matter, largely concerning teaching and professional positions held by Bassett.
  Arranged alphabetically by name, topic, or type of material.
  - Address book, 1927, undated (Box 33)
  - American Historical Association
    - Committees
      - Appointments to, 1895-1919, (2 folders)
      - Lists of, 1906-1927, undated, (2 folders) (Box 34)
      - Minutes and reports, 1909-1927, undated, (9 folders)
    - Correspondence (Box 35)
      - Oct. 1918-Dec. 1921, (10 folders)
      - Jan. 1922-Sept. 1924, (9 folders) (Box 36)
      - Oct. 1924-Dec. 1925, (9 folders) (Box 37)
      - Jan. 1926-Feb. 1928, (6 folders) (Box 38)
    - Executive Council
      - Annual business meeting, 1921-1927
      - Minutes and dockets
        - 1914-1921, (2 folders)
        - 1922-1927, undated (Box 39)
      - Secretary's reports, 1919-1927, undated
    - Financial statements and reports, 1916-1925, undated
    - Membership lists and statistics, 1920-1925
    - Miscellany, 1920-1926, undated
    - Other organizations, 1920-1927, undated
    - Printed matter, 1910-1927, undated
  - Condolences on death, 1928, (2 folders)
  - Democratic National Committee, advisory group (Box 40)
    - General correspondence, 1920, undated, (4 folders)
    - Miscellany, 1920, undated See also Oversize
    - Notes, 1920, undated
    - Veterans Cox-Roosevelt Club, 1920, undated, (2 folders)
    - Writings and statements, 1919-1920, undated, (5 folders) (Box 41)
  - Historical and research organizations, 1899-1926
  - Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, Md., notebook, 1892
  - Notebooks, 1896-1897, 1924, undated (Box 42)
  - Publishers
    - Contracts, 1902-1916
    - Royalty statements, 1915-1928
  - Real estate and financial matters, 1906-1924, undated
  - Smith College, Northampton, Mass.
    - Correspondence, 1909-1918, undated
    - History Department
      - Curriculum, notes on, 1918, undated
      - Examination questions, grades, and assignments, 1907-1919, undated
      - Reports and minutes, 1915-1919, undated
      - Smith College Studies in History, 1915-1917, undated
    - Printed matter, 1906, 1914-1917
    - Reports and regulations, 1909-1917, undated
  - Trinity College, Randolph County, N.C. (later Duke University, Durham, N.C.)
    - Miscellany, 1897-1960, undated
    - Newspaper clippings, 1895-1978, undated, (4 folders) (Box 43)
- Lectures and Speeches, 1902-1926 (Box 43-47)
  Drafts, outlines, and notes from lectures and speeches delivered by Bassett.
  Lectures are organized by place delivered and alphabetically therein by topic. Speeches are organized alphabetically by topic.
  - Lecture material (Box 43)
    - Smith College, Northampton, Mass., United States history, undated
      - On chronological periods
        - 1492-1788, (2 folders)
        - 1789-1815, (3 folders); (1 folder) (Box 44)
        - 1816-1860, (2 folders)
        - 1861-1865
        - 1866-1877, (2 folders)
        - 1878-1919, (1 folder); (2 folders) (Box 45)
      - On general topics
    - Unidentified academic institutions, undated
      - European history, (4 folders)
      - Greek and Roman history
      - United States history (Box 46)
        - On chronological periods
          - 1492-1788, (4 folders)
          - 1789-1865
          - 1866-1925, (2 folders)
        - On general topics (Box 47)
          - African-American history
          - Legal and constitutional history
          - Nineteenth-century historians
          - North Carolina
    - Yale University, New Haven, Conn., summer school, undated
  - Speeches
    - African-American history, undated